Sensei, sensei, it's time to start.
Uh-oh, that's right. I keep forgetting.
Radio Eikai is Hiroto Onishi, the English teacher of Artless Kame.
I'm happy to know we have David to let you know when you forget.
This is Akino Rosa.
And I'm David Evans. That's what I'm here for, folks.
Let's get started.
Lesson 138
説明ルールその4 通負停止
今日のキーセンテンスはこちら I bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate
同宿の後ろにトゥーフテーションを並べればその説明 どういった説明になるのかは文脈によって様々なバリエーションがあります
それでは今日のダイアログから確認しましょう
ケガからすっかり回復したフランケーヌ・スタイン博士と
アンドロイドのジーニーが話しています
博士は会期祝いのパーティーを提案しますが
Well, Genie, I'm able to walk by myself again
The doctor said there are no problems with my hip now
I'm happy to know you can walk again, Dr. Stein
Genie
i want to thank you and frankie for helping me it was our pleasure dr stein listen genie
let's have a party at home later i bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate
but we cannot drink alcohol dr stein it is bad for us oh my yes yes that's right i keep forgetting
それでは、ダイアログの内容を確認しましょう。
Well, Jeannie, I'm able to walk by myself again.
The doctor said there are no problems with my hip now.
さてと、ジーニー、私はまた一人で歩けるようになったよ。
医師によると、私の腰にはもう何も問題がないそうだ。
I'm happy to know you can walk again, Dr. Stein.
スタイン博士、
博士がまた歩けるようになってよかったです。
ジーニー、君とフランキーが私の手助けをしてくれたことをありがたく思っているよ。
さあ、for helping me、これは理由を表すforですね。
It was our pleasure, Dr. Stein.
どういたしまして、スタイン博士。
Listen, Jeannie, let's have a party at home later.
I bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate.
いいかい、ジーニー。
あとで家でパーティーをしよう。
お祝いにシャンパンのボトルを買ってあるんだ。
But we cannot drink alcohol, Dr. Stein.
It is bad for us.
でも、スタイン博士、
私たちはお酒を飲めません。
体に悪い影響があるので。
Oh, my.
Yes, yes, that's right.
I keep forgetting.
ああ、いけない。
そう、その通りだ。君たちがアンドロイドだということをいつも忘れてしまうんだ。
Grammar and Vocabulary
文法と語彙のポイントを確認します。
まず確認するのは、スタイン博士の最初のセリフから。
I'm able to walk by myself again.
私はまた一人で歩けます。
In this sentence, it is used to emphasize that it is not a more simple can, but be able to, what, what can be done, because it is emphasized that it can be done.
I couldn't walk after the injury, but I can do it now.
It includes the strong feeling of able, be able, and the ability to be impressed, be able to, which is chosen.
Now, let's check another line from Dr. Stein.
医師は私の腰には今何も問題がないと言いました レッスン129でリポート文に伴う
時勢の一致について説明しましたが この文の従属説の動詞は
時勢の一致は起こっていません 時勢の一致は絶対の規則ではないのです
If this sentence simply says, I said, what is the doctor? If you just report what you said in the past, your self-esteem will be the same, and it will be, there were.
However, as it is clear from the fact that I am adding now in this sentence, I am strongly aware of the current state that there is no problem now.
単に発言内容のリポートにとどまらず
今そうなのだと特別な意識が加わる場合
時勢の一致は起こらないのです
それではもう一度ダイアログを聞いてみましょう
Well, Genie, I'm able to walk by myself again
The doctor said there are no problems with my hip now
I'm happy to know you can walk again, Dr. Stein
i want to thank you and frankie for helping me it was our pleasure dr stein listen genie
let's have a party at home later i bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate
but we cannot drink alcohol dr stein it is bad for us oh my yes yes that's right i keep forgetting
Target forms.
会話に役立つ典型表現を身につけましょう。
まずは今日のキーセンテンスを改めて確認します。
I bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate.
私は祝うためにシャンパンのボトルを買いました。
動詞句の説明にはトゥーフテーシも頻繁に使われます。
動詞句の後ろに並べればいいだけですよ。
通負停止による説明には目的、感情の原因、結果、判断の根拠などがありますが、もちろん通負停止自体にこうした意味があるわけではありません。
シャンパンのボトルを買ったなら、何のためにそうしたのか、目的が説明としてふさわしい。そこから目的の使い方が生まれているだけです。
さあ、頑張っていきましょう。
同宿の後ろにトゥーフセッションを並べるだけですよ。
I bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate.
多々。
もう一度いきましょう。
I bought a bottle of champagne to celebrate.
それでは、その他の例も一緒に身につけていきましょう。
I came here to learn.
私は学ぶためにここに来ました。
目的を表すtoフテーシュは大変ポピュラー。
紛れもなく目的であることを表すために
in order to, so as to
といったフレーズが使われることもあります。
I'm happy to know you can walk again.
あなたがまた歩けるようになったと知って嬉しく思います。
感情の説明としてその原因、感情プラス感情の原因は品質コンビネーションです。
We opened the box to find it was empty.
私たちはその箱を開けてそれが空だと分かりました。
オープン・デ・ボックスの結果を示すのがトゥー以下。
デ・ファインドは予期せぬ。
しばしば悪い出来事との遭遇を表す決まり文句。
You must be crazy to believe that.
そんなことを信じるなんてあなたは気が変であるに違いありません。
マスク、何々に違いないを含む動詞句の後ろにトゥー不定詞。
総判断を下す根拠を示しています
OK, OK, OK
Practice time, everyone
Next up in our 動詞句プラス説明 series is 通不定詞
Just put it after the 動詞句 and you're done
Ta-da! Let's practice
Here we go
Came here to learn
I came here to learn
I came here to learn.
Great work. Let's keep going.
I'm happy to know you can walk again.
One more time.
Keep going.
We opened the box to find it was empty.
All right, and let's wrap up with one more.
You must be crazy to believe that.
Unlock your potential.
Repetition is the key.
Great work!
GRAMMAR IN ACTION!
私たちのおすすめは?
I do shakyō to relax.
It's very calming.
You should try it sometime.
I do shakyō to relax.
It's very calming.
You should try it sometime.
目的を表すto不定詞
calm 落ち着かせるから派生した形容詞
calming は心を落ち着かせる
では音読練習です。
I do shakyō to relax.
It's very calming. You should try it sometime.
それでは次の問題。
あなたが新しい友人を作っているのがわかり、うれしく思います。よかったね。
さあ、これはノーヒントでいきましょう。
私たちのおすすめは?
I'm happy to see you're making new friends.
Good for you.
感情、I'm happyの原因をto see以下が説明。
seeの後ろは説、何々であることがわかる。
Good for youは、よかったね、えらいね。
では音読練習です。
I'm happy to see you're making new friends.
Good for you.
それではもう一問。
あんなふうに反応するなんて、
彼はストレスがたまっているに違いありません。
彼は普段とてもマナーがいいのです。
さあ、反応する。
これはReact。
私たちのおすすめは
He must be stressed to react that way. He's usually very well-mannered.
Must be stressed to react that way.
Sensei, it's time to wrap up the program.
Oh, sorry. I keep forgetting.
Soredewa.
Bye!